So in our last video, we just saw that we were going to try and create RSA decryption and we saw that
we needed a decryption key that obeyed this rule here where p to the power e times the mod m gets you
back to your original plaintext letter.
I claim that this exists and I'm going to show you how to find it.
But before we get that, I'm going to need a couple of mathematical results known as Fermat's Little
Theorem and the Chinese Remainder Theorems.
Let's take a look at these results.
And these are proper results.
They're actually called theorems, and they actually have names which shows you that they are proper
mathematical results and important results, too.
So let's start with a famous little theorem named after Ferma.
You may have heard of Fermat's Last Theorem.
This is Fermat's Little Theorem.
This is a fact about prime numbers.
So it's just a little fact about prime numbers.
Let's see what it is.
So let's take a Q.
If Q is a prime and X an integer, then this is my little fact.
So x integer co prime to Q very important then this is my fact.
X to the power.
Q minus one is congruent to one mode.
Q.
Okay.
Just seems like some mathematical fact.
We're going to prove it, though.
Let's have a look at the proof of this.
So we've said that X and Q are co prime.
X was our integer and Q was a prime number was in there k prime oh k prime warning bells and I know
what k prime means.
It means there exists integers, s and t such that I can write a combination s x plus t q equal one
because one will be their greatest common divisor.
So we've got this here x plus two equals one in most Q arithmetic, which is what I'm going to write
down next.
T Q would disappear as a multiple of Q is a zero so I can write this is s x congruent to one mod q.
And that means that X has a multiplicative inverse, which is s.
Module IQ.
In other words, s is the inverse of x.
They cancel out, so you get 1ak.
So x that integer has a multiplicative inverse and I've even told you what it is.
It's s next.
Imagine we have two multiples of x, here's a multiple and lots of x and let's say that is congruent
to n lots of x mod q.
If that occurs, we could multiply both sides by s, which would cancel out the x and you would get
m congruent to n mod Q.
Now that's going to help us because that means no two items in this list can be congruent.
So what?
What is the list?
x2x3x you get the idea for x, etc. up to two minus one x.
None of those values can be congruent in modulo Q because they've all got different coefficients of
x.
This means the list is just this list and written in a different way.
This means the list is simply what are the remainders in March?
Q It's 1 to 3 dot, dot, dot.
Q Minus one in modulo.
Q although possibly in a different order.
So it might not be exactly the same list in the same order, but it is the same list.
If both lists are the same, multiplying all the terms in each list gives this right.
Let's do this.
I'm going to multiply this list first.
The first list we had with the x2x3x, multiply everything together.
So what are going to get?
We're going to get one X times two X times three x.
All the coefficients are going to be one times, two times three times four, optically minus one,
which is Q minus one factorial.
And would I know the x is together x times x times x times x is q minus one.
Lots of x.
I'm going to write that as.
X to the power.
Q minus one written it that way and that is congruent to and multiplying everything together on the
second list because it's the same list.
So I'm going to multiply all these values together on the second, which is this one times, two times,
three times optically minus one, which is Q minus one factorial.
And remember this was all in mod q arithmetic since Q is prime.
It is co prime to all integers, 1 to 3, optically minus one.
And it is co prime to a number like that, then that number would have an inverse and you could be able
to cancel it out to get rid of it.
Therefore, we can cancel out these factorial.
So we can cancel out the term Q minus one factorial on both sides.
And then this leaves what we get.
So we just cancel out the key minus one factorial.
We would get X to the power.
Q minus one is congruent to one.
What Q?
And again, which is.
And the proof.
That is what I was trying to prove.
That is fair analysis.
Say that as it stands, you don't see what we're going to do with this yet.
But let's take it let's just have a look at an example of the market to fail and let's use some numbers
to see it working as take x equals four.
As an integer and a prime.
Let's take a q equals five.
Then let's take a look at well, what does firm R0 Theorem say?
Says Take X, which is four to the power Q minus one s five minus one which is going to be four to the
powerful minus.
Well, write that in it's equal to four to the power four and that is equal to 256.
But here's the important thing that is congruent to one mod five, and that is not a coincidence.
That was a conclusion guaranteed by Fermi's Little Theorem.
That's exactly what I was expecting by firm Little Theorem.
And it wasn't a coincidence.
It's guaranteed to happen.
That would always happen under no circumstances.
Fair Master two Theorem Our Next Theorem.
I'm going to be straight on our next theorem again.
Cool theory with a name Chinese remainder theorem for this one if.
A is congruent to be marked and.
And a is congruent to be mod n.
So we've got two conferences here.
So if that is true with M and N.
Co prime integers, so they are co prime integers.
Then here's our conclusion.
A is congruent to be marked m times end.
So if you have a congruence that is true modern and a congruent that is true mod n with these modulus
values k prime then the congruent is still true in mod m and I will prove that proof.
This take and a is congruent.
Let's just take our set up really a is going to be modem.
And a.
Congruent to be model then.
Now we go way back to our definition of modular arithmetic and from the definition of modular take.
I can tell you there exists integers that's called in K1 and K2.
I'll put it here in this gap such that the difference of A and B is a multiple of the modulus.
So in our case we have a minus.
B is equal to k1m.
And A minus B is equal to K to N.
That is the definition of modular arithmetic.
So yeah, well, A-minus B here and A minus B here.
So I can just say these things are equal.
k1m is equal to k to n.
Okay.
Therefore m strictly divides k to n.
Yes, this K2 n is a multiple of m and strictly divides K2 n, but since m.
An n r code prime.
That means M doesn't divide and it must divide q.
This means m strictly divides k to.
And therefore there exists another integer, let's call it K three.
There exists an integer k three such that k two is equal to k3m.
So K2 is a multiple of em as well.
And finally, we can conclude A minus B.
It's equal to K to N.
I know that from what one of the second line here in the proof that it is but k two can be replaced
now with k3m so this is equal to k three and N and that's it really because that is the definition of
a congruent to B mod.
M n and the proof.
Very good.
So that is, Chinese remained there.
So now we've got that in our pocket.
We've got that under our belt.
And we're going to use these two results in what's coming up next, which is finding how to decrypt
RSA.
So this decryption result is what we call a corollary.
It's an easy consequence of a theorem or proposition.
As I say, decryption is a corollary of the results.
We've just done.
Fantastic.
And the Chinese remained a theorem.
And I think we'll take a proper look at this in the next video.