So we're coming near the end of our course now, but we've got a couple of more sections to go.
And I just want to end off by showing you a way to authenticate who is sending your message, and it
uses RSA.
So we call this signatures or digital signatures.
And if I go to our notes, in fact, I'm not asking you to write anything in for this part.
I'm just going to explain the method.
So the intention of RSA is to in cipher using your value e and then decipher using the value D but in
fact the rows of E and D are interchangeable.
You could in fact and cipher your message using the value D and then decipher the message using the
value B if you wanted to.
This has a very important function in authenticating messages, so consider two correspondence.
John and Mary, I think I want you to give Alice and Bob a day off.
So John and Mary are sending each of the messages, each have their own public key, which are known
to everyone, and each have their own private key known only to themselves.
Let's say Mary's public key is giving you some values.
E is 8023 modulus 24,257 and John's Public Key E 8993 and a modulus of 11,435.
These are this is the public information.
Now, John is going to send a message and it says, meet you at six, John.
So he signs off with his name that John and written in blocks we might break this up into blocks remember
that prevents frequency analysis so I've broken it open two blocks of two there so we've got meet you
at six John or in numbers I now turn those into numbers like that so we get these blocks of numbers.
The last two of those blocks, the last well, eight digits is the signature, John.
Now, how can Mary know that?
The message really is from John?
One way is for John to use his private key John and ciphers his signature using his private key so that
it reads this value like these numbers here.
So now we have this message.
But John has insisted the signature at the end using his private key John now in ciphers that message
using Mary's public key.
So now takes all of that including his signature at the end and in cipher is that with Mary's public
key then sends it to Mary.
Mary receives the message she will then decrypted using her private key to produce this message.
And Mary will then extract that last bit at the end the signature.
And knowing that the message is supposed to be from John, Mary applies John's public key to his signature
to get these values here.
So Mary is now decrypting that bit at the end, using John's public key.
Finally putting all this together, Mary will get the message.
Meet you at six, John.
And the only one who could have made that possible is John himself.
The only person who could have encrypted that signature at the end with John's private key is John himself.
That is the idea.
Note, though, just like before with RSA, it is more secure to use different RSA keys for encryption
and signing.
So you might have to RSA.
He's going on and you will still need padding and breaking open the blocks and all those things.
We need to prevent people from stealing our messages using RSA.
Yes, padding should be used for message signing as it is for message encryption.
Okay, so that's a really clever idea and that's all I wanted to say about signatures, but a really
clever way of using RSA.
Now we really are getting near the end and that's the end of public key cryptography.
And then just as the very last thing, I want you to take a brief look at the future of cryptography.
So one more video.
I'm going to have a look at the future.