Now let's take a look at the solutions for this breaking RSA exercises.
I start with a few notes.
First, I say we're going to use two digit numbers now.
So A is 0001, Z is 25.
That just makes things nice and same size.
I say that the following ciphertext contain no padding, which means you can break them using the methods
I described in the course.
And finally, I say you can perform these calculations with a computer or Wolfram Alpha.
So let's do question one.
And I ask you to encode the word elephant as two digit numbers just to get that point across.
So elephant is the word.
So elephant.
And then I'm asking you to write us two digit numbers.
So that is zero 411 zero 415
0700 13 and 19.
He split the word into blocks of two letters and write the numerical values of each block.
So we are now going to split the word into blocks of two letters e l, e, p, h, a and an t, and
will write the values of that.
And that is just 0411.
041507001319.
We are now going to encrypt these blocks using RSA.
With modulus m equals 2773 and encryption key E equals 1147, which is not too hard to do with a computer.
How can you say if a writing hour blocks?
And if not.
Like that.
We have our numerical values.
04110415.
07001319.
And now we hit it with the formula p to the power e mode and.
And yes, with our computers we can to say that that is going to be 1816
1429.
1225.
And 1511.
So those phone numbers will be the ciphertext.
But I want to point out that this hides the frequency of the letter E and it hides that A, which has
always been zero so far.
Now it's hiding that A as well.
So now let's have a look at some breaking RSA methods.
So these were described in the course notes.
Let's take a look.
So we have a stolen ciphertext reading here.
So we've got three numbers here.
It was sent using RSA without padding and a public key of M equals 2773 and E equals 1147 is the same
numbers I used before.
So work out the original message using a chosen plaintext attack.
So we think the ciphertext is one of these four possible words.
So because it's all animal themed, you might be putting mongoose, rabbit or raccoon.
Which word is it?
So really, we just test out these four words using the public key and then see which one matches the
stolen ciphertext.
Well, we've got three numbers here, and these are like six letter words or eight letter words.
So they're written in blocks and it's probably a six letter word in blocks of two.
So I'm going to exclude Mongoose straight away.
So a mongoose is too long.
Mongoose is too long.
Now, that would be a problem if it had padding.
If it has padding, then the padding makes all these words the same length, which makes it harder to
work out which one is which.
Now let's test out some of these words baboon, rabbit or raccoon.
Let's test out the first two letters of rabbit or raccoon because they both start with an R and then
A.
So if I encrypt r a, then r a is encoded as 1700.
And let's hit that with the public key.
To the public key, we take 1700 raise to the encryption number, 1147, and that is going to be congruent
to 1015 in March.
2000 to 773.
There we go.
2773.
That matches the first block of the ciphertext.
So.
Oh, that's a clue.
So he's not going to be back in I think it's rabbit or it's raccoon, but I'm going to test the next
pair of letters to find out.
I'm going to use.
Let's try raccoon.
So she used the C oh.
So if I use the C L, I'm going to get 0214.
And I going to hit that.
With the encryption key.
And if I do that, I'm going to get to go for for.
In March 2773 AU That matches the second black hour, so it's probably going to be raccoon.
And if you wanted to, you could test out B.B. here in Rabbit and you'll find that it will not work.
So if you do that, you test out B.B. it would be 0101.
And if we encrypt that with our encryption key, that is going to be 1353.
But it doesn't match the ciphertext.
So yes, raccoon sounds right to me.
And indeed, if you keep going, e check out the last block there.
The O and that would be one for.
One three.
And if you encrypt that.
No surprises, but it will encrypt to be the final block in the cipher text.
So it is the word raccoon after all.
Okay, so let's have a look at question three.
We've got a stone in ciphertext again.
Those are the values.
I wasn't using RSA without padding and the same public key as before.
This time I've decided to use a chosen ciphertext attack using x equals two.
So first of all, we're going to have a look and see that X in our code prime.
So, okay, prime.
I know what that means.
So we could do have Euclid's algorithm here.
But it's not too hard.
Euclid's algorithm.
So we do that.
So we're looking to show that X and M.
Okay, prime.
That's right.
M which is 2773 on the left.
That is equal to something times two to something.
It turns out that the coefficient there is 1386 and the remainder is one.
And that ends Euclid's algorithm straight away for us.
That's nice.
So, yes, they all k prime.
The greatest common divisor will be one.
So what is the multiplicative inverse of X in modulo m?
Well, I need to reverse Euclid's algorithm here so that I have one equal some sort of combination of
the original numbers, which is two.
And.
2773.
Well, that's quite easy to reverse.
And so that's just one lot of 2773 and subtracting the 1386.
So now it's actually a -1386 there.
So it's that coefficient that will be the inverse.
So if x equals two.
If X equals two, then the inverse, which I'll call x dash.
Is congruent to the -1386, and I could leave it like that, but let's make it positive.
And so I'll just add on the modulus to make it 1387.
Again, that is in MOD 2773.
Let's continue.
So the next part asks you to work out X to the power e in mind.
And so we know what x is.
It's two, we know what E is.
It is 1147 and yet use a computer because the answer is going to be 1134 and that's in March.
2773.
Part D then asks you to create a second cipher.
C2, which is C1 multiplied by that value, just worked out.
So, so c1.
Is the ciphertext, which is a178.
1735.
And 0903.
And we're multiplying that to get C to we're multiplying that by the value is just what out the 1134.
And we get.
21961423.
And 0765.
So that is our cipher too, which doesn't mean anything, but that is our fake cipher.
I am now able to have cipher two deciphered and I will receive a decryption which looks like this.
What was the original message?
So we have our 0061.
Our zero 0 to 6.
And 1208.
Now, when you have that deciphered, the result is that it's just a plain text multiplied by x and
mod m.
So now to finish off to get the plain text, which is multiply this thing by the X in.
So we've taking the line above and then multiply that by x inverse and that's in mod and.
X inverse we worked out, which was the 1387 that was from part B.
So I'm multiplying by that value and I'm doing that in modular arithmetic.
And the final answer is going to be 1417.
0013.
Zero six.
Zero four.
And finally, we turn out two letters.
What we get when we turn it into letters, we get o, o, a and g e.
It's a return of the surprise.
Orange.
There you go.
So orange is coming back just like we had at the beginning of this course.
Finally, let's have a look at question for another stone in ciphertext.
So a question for SAS.
Here we have a stolen ciphertext.
It was sent using RSA without padding and the same public key we've had before.
Modulus M equal to 2773 and encryption key E equal to 1147.
This time I'm going to ask you to break this cipher by centralising the modulus and working out the
original message.
And I'm not going to give you the solution to this answer.
I'm going to leave this as a challenge.
This was our last question for the course, and I think it would be nice to leave that as a challenge
to our no prizes.
We are playing for glory.
But if you do get this answer really well done, you can send me a message if you like, on Udemy,
telling me that you have solved this message and I will send you no prizes whatsoever.
But I will send you some congratulations.
Yes, we're just playing for smugness here, so good luck with that.
So that's the final challenge and that is the final solution video.
So I hope you enjoy the next couple of lecture videos.