Now it's time to bring our story up to date with modern Internet encryption.
I talked about having that locked box idea and sending your message to your friend.
Now, I said that the code breaker, the spy could brute force this open to smashing the box open.
I talked about picking the lock.
And I also talked about someone stealing the key.
So this is going to be another way of preventing people from stealing the key because we're not going
to give out any keys.
So this is called public key cryptography.
So let's go to our notes and we'll have a look at our first example of this.
We'll start with just a little introduction here.
So a cipher system is symmetric or one key if it is easy to reduce the decryption key from the encryption
key.
In practice, these two keys are often identical.
So that's kind of what we've been seeing so far.
So something like an additive cipher, multiplicative cipher, or even a general substitution cipher.
You can work out the inverse key from the original key.
This creates the problem of exchanging keys without the keys being stolen.
So if you are the spy and you steal the key, then you will be able to decode the messages to solve
this problem.
Two schemes were developed that don't require any secret channels.
You don't have to exchange keys in any sort of secret way.
So this is known as public key cryptography.
So there are no secrets involved.
You can just give away the keys.
The first was devised by Diffie and Hellman in 1976, and the second was devised by Rivest Shamir and
Adelman in 1977.
We're going to describe both these ideas, along with some small examples, but the first that we're
going to look at is the Diffie Hellman Key Exchange.
So the idea with this one is you both create the two participants, both create part of a shared key.
So they start with a shared base.
The first person creates part of the key.
The second person creates part of the key.
They then exchange what they've made.
They both then complete the key.
And those two participants will have a complete key each which they can use for sending each of other
messages.
But then if you have the spy who wants to steal the keys, well, you're sending only partial keys backwards
and forwards.
So that's the idea.
But we'll do that in a more mathematical way.
So the idea of Diffie Hellman Key Exchange is to create, like I said, a shared key, starting with
a shared base.
Each participant makes a partial key, which are then exchanged and used to complete the final shared
key.
Here are or here is an example using exponents where all exchanges can be made on an insecure channel.
So you can pass this information backwards and forwards in public.
So let Q be a prime key for a prime instead of P for prime, because we used plot already for plaintext
letters.
So Q is a prime number.
Then there exists an integer x, right, such that the powers of x generate all values modulo q.
So that's just something that is true.
I'm giving this to you as a fact.
So when you're working in modulo Q arithmetic and Q is a prime, then there will be an integer that
can then generate all the possible values modulo Q which if you remember all the possible remainders
modulo Q So step one of this key exchange you've got Alyson Bob as they as we traditionally have.
And first of all, they share their common information.
And common information is it's a modulus of.
Q So you can tell people what that number is and the generator.
X Again, you can tell people what that is.
Then step two Alice has a secret integer and we'll call that a a for Alice.
And Alice will calculate this value X to the power.
A So it's X to the power.
A So we're talking about X times, x times X a number of times, and that will be in modern Q arithmetic.
So you'll have a smaller number than not because and most Q arithmetic means you look at the remainder.
And Bob will do the same.
Bob has a secret integer B for Bob and calculates using that generator that everyone knows using x.
Raising to the power b this time.
And that is in mod q arithmetic.
So Alice and Bob have made partial keys and they now swap.
So they swap those partial keys.
And then finally Alice is going to calculate X to the power B that is Bob's partial key and raise that
to Alice's secret number, which is a switch X to the power B to the power A and that will be mod Q.
And Bob.
Well, Bob takes Odyssey's partial key, which is exit the power aid and raises to his secret number.
So brazen to Power B.
Now we've got X to the power, eh?
To the power B, and that is a mod Q arithmetic.
So that's what is in Bob have done.
But this is great because they have created a shared key.
This is a shared key because.
X to the power A to the power B is going to be congruent to.
I put this in a bracket now x the power of B to the power a mod q is going to mean that I was in power
will now have the same value.
They're going to have the same numerical value which they will be able to use to encrypt and decrypt
messages.
This is only the key.
This is not sending the message itself.
So he's now created a number and they both got the same number and then they can use that in whatever
cipher they've decided to use.
And it might be something simple.
It might be something like a multiplicative cipher.
That is what some of the code l gammel encryption uses this idea and then takes that secret number they've
created in a multiplicative cipher, using this as a multiplicative key in modulo Q.
It's a split in that last gap that so it doesn't even have to be a difficult cipher once you've exchanged
the key.
Okay, let's do an example of this with some small numbers so that you get a better feel for it.
So let's take an X to be two, X equals two and we'll have a prime number, and that is Q And that is
going to be, I'm going to say 29 as my prime number, starting with this base.
So that is public information that everyone can know.
The two participants use the secret integers.
Let's say Alice has picked a equals five and Bob has picked B equals 12 and they're going to create
their partial keys.
So what does that mean?
So they take the generator, which is two, and I'm going to do Alice first.
So two to the power A, which is five and that will be well we can just calculate that if you want to.
That is equal to 32.
So two to the power five and we're in March 29 arithmetic here that is congruent to three Mar 29 arithmetic
because there is three left over and what is Bob going to do?
So I'll end here and then Bob.
Bob is taking that generator to raising two secret number 12 and he's going to create something quite
large actually that in this case 4096.
And then we're interested in that value.
In my 29 arithmetic, which I will tell you right now, is a seven mod 29.
You can get a calculator, a computer to work that out, but I am going to show you methods of working
out something like that for yourself by hand.
But now we are going to exchange those values.
So Alice and Bob exchange their values.
Alice receives Bob's value and it was seven and will raise seven to hash secret number, which is a
five.
So it's to the power five.
And then that is something I'm going to tell you what it is.
16,807 and we go and was that in mod 29 arithmetic?
Again, just let me tell you, it is congruent to 16 mod 29 and what's Bob going to do?
So Bob has received Alice's number, which was a three, and that's going to be raised to the power
12, and that is whether it's going to be equal to a very large number,
531,441.
And again, I will tell you that that is congruent to 16 March 29, which is nice because you get the
same number as we expected to.
The two participants now have a shared key of 16, and they can use that however they want in whatever
cipher they want.
Now, in real life, the values of A, B and Q are much larger.
So when you're really using this procedure, you will be using larger values of A, B and Q.
You're going to get some very large numbers in these calculations.
Again, you could do these with computers and things, however, and when I was taught how to do modular
arithmetic in this kind of thing, and I was taught how to do it by hand because we didn't really have
the computers around to do this for us.
And yeah, so I'm going to teach you how to do it by hand.
So often you can do this by hand if you notice by observation.
And some sort of way to break up the calculation so that some parts of the calculation are easy numbers,
like small numbers, so that some parts of the calculation become zero mod, whatever one might, whatever
or two might, whatever it is.
Those zeros, ones and twos then obviously are very easy to start calculating.
I'll show you an example of how you might do that.
So this is you trying to do something by hand.
So to calculate to to the power.
12 March 29.
So what I'm not going to do I'm not going to calculate to to the power 12 but I might notice by observation
something that is easy to use.
Maybe I'll see that two to the power five which is 32 that is congruent to three Mar 29.
And then there's two to the power 12.
We could break it up to to the power 12 and that is equal to if you are happy with how powers work,
we could break up the two to the power 12 into two to the power five squared.
Due to the power five squared is two to power ten.
And what's this over two squared.
And that would be two to power 12.
So I've broken it up and I can replace because it's modular arithmetic, I can replace two to the power
five with this much nicer number three so that two, two power five in the bracket is now three.
So it's three squared and two squared.
So I'll just leave us two squared for now.
But obviously that is four.
And so that then is congruent to three squared times two squared.
So we can do that however you want nine times four and that then becomes 36.
Much more manageable and then that is congruent to seven mod 29, which is what we expected.
That is what I had before.
So yes, you can do these things by hand.
Again, it is really just by observation.
So you just sort of notice some easy numbers and then break up the calculation.
Even though x.
Q and extra power a mod q.
An X to the power of B mod q are sent in the clear.
So on an insecure channel you just you can just exchange these numbers and everyone can find them if
they want to.
It's still very difficult for your spy or codebreaker to work out what X to do.
Power A, B mod q will be, which is the shared key.
It's very difficult to work that out from the information you've stolen, and this is called the discrete,
logarithmic or logarithm problem.
That is a hard thing to solve, which is why we can use it at the procedure created a shared key because
the order of the exponents didn't matter and in other words they commute.
We talked about computing before we talk about computing ciphers.
This is kind of the same idea.
Although we're not committing to ciphers here, we're using a procedure that commits to create the shared
key.
So the order of exponents, I don't matter.
They can mute.
And you could use this same idea with any other procedure that has some element that can meet.
So you could replace exponents with any operation that commutes.
So here's an example.
Nothing like the exponents, and it's called elliptic curve cryptography, which is something we use
today on the internet.
And so to exchange keys.
So elliptic curve cryptography uses curves with our own kind of addition.
Adding two points on the curve is defined to be the operation of drawing a straight line through the
points, finding where the line intersects on the curve, and then reflecting that point in the x axis.
Let me just break down for I said there.
So this is called an electric curve.
There's a picture there underneath.
So it's this wiggly curve.
So a particular kind of mathematical curve.
And I've got 2.2, I've got point Q on point R and I've drawn a line through Q and on and intersects
the curve one more time at a third point.
There it is.
And I, what I do next is I actually reflect that in the x axis.
So I actually get a point down here and I call that point Q plus R.
Now, this rather strange definition of addition does work a lot like the addition you would know,
and importantly it would commute as well.
So, yes, importantly, this definition of addition can meet multiples of a point, can be found quickly
by combination of doubling and addition.
So let's say I want you to work out a multiple of Q so I've got my Q here and if I want to work out
a multiple Okay.
Well, first thing I could do is double it.
So I'd have Q plus Q would mean drawing a line here through Q itself and then it would intersect.
So probably quite high up over here, I would intersect and create a point to.
Q Then I could double to get four Q and I could double for Q and get eight Q So it's very easy to double
that point, and then I could work out multiples of Q using those values.
And if I wanted to work out ten lots of Q, I would take eight plus two lots of Q, add those together
with this operation so we can find multiples of a point by doubling and then adding.
Now we're going to create a key.
So this is the same idea as Stephanie Hellman, but using this elliptic curve.
So the two participants, they're going to start by sharing a starting point, which I'm going to call
P capital P, so they share a starting point, common knowledge.
They know the curve, they know the starting point.
Each participant then create a secret multiple of P.
So let's say we have our Alison Bob.
Alice creates a lots of P and Bob creates B, lots of P, so some multiple of that a point which are
then exchanged.
So they swap those points.
Both participants, they multiply those exchanged points by their secret value to create a point A,
B, P, and the coordinates of that point can be used as the shared key.
So you get a value using the coordinates.
At that point, you can then use that value as a key.
Again, it could be in any other site that you want, could be a multiple.
Negative cipher fi, something like that.
It's very difficult to work out the final point from this information that is exchanged.
So information that is public is the electric curve.
The starting point is public information.
Then if you're a spy, you might steal a lots of P and be lots of P, but even with that stolen information
at that final point is very difficult to work out.
And this is even harder if the calculations are done in modular arithmetic.
So the way I've described it so far, I've done it with a curve, like like a graph, like a curve you
might see on a graph.
I bet you could do all these calculations in modular arithmetic as well, so they wouldn't be a nice
continuous curve like that, but it would be the same sort of idea just in modular arithmetic, and
that would make the point seem completely unrelated.
You're just exchanging what seems like random points, very difficult then to work out your shared key.
So that's tricky.
Hellman Exchange a brilliant idea and it is used today to exchange keys.
But next, I'm going to show you another idea that is used again, public key cryptography.
Another example of that, and that is called RSA, are also used on the Internet.
Well, have a look at that in the next video.