Now that we have these mathematical results, we should be ready to have a look at RSA decryption.
So let's take notes and here we go.
So RSA decryption here is going to be using Fermat's Little Theorem and the Chinese remainder theorem.
So first we're going to recall the RSA set up.
If you remember how we set up our RSA, there were two primes, Q1 and Q2.
That's right.
But in.
So we got Q1, Q2 primes.
We got a modulus M, which is equal to Q one times Q two.
We have this thing called A, which is equal to Q one minus one in brackets multiplied by Q two minus
one.
And we had E, which was our encryption key, and that is an integer K prime to A that is the RSA setup.
Now there is a decryption key where kind of equality for decryption such that x to the power e times
d is congruent to x mark m so I claim it exists a decryption key that would return you back to your
original value.
Nice for all integers x.
The decryption key is the multiplicative inverse of E modulo a.
And I e e times d is congruent to one mod a so yes, that's actually rather surprising because mod a
coming out here now instead of being a mod Q mod A Yeah.
The decryption key is the multiplicative inverse of E modulo a Well, I have to prove this, so let's
do that.
Here is our proof.
So if we have E and a CO prime which is part of the set up, if in A-OK prime, then warning bells e
and a co prime means we can do this s times e plus t time a equals one.
Yes, absolutely.
Equivalently, then we're saying s e is congruent to one mod a s because there's t a is a multiple of
A that disappears.
So we've got a 1 to 1 mod a therefore the multiplicative inverse of E modulo a is s.
It's that coefficient there in front of the E and let's let D decryption key equal s.
So this exists.
We know it exists because of what we've just said.
But does it decode messages to show that x to the power e d congruent to x mod m for all integers x.
What we're going to do is first we're going to prove that that is true in mod q one and we're going
to show is true in Mod Q two.
Then you can use the Chinese remainder theorem, which would then prove that it is true in modulo m,
which I might I'll write this here, which is Q one times Q two.
So let's break this down and prove its true in March.
Q one.
Well, first, if Q one divides X, then x is congruent to zero mod q one because x would be a multiple
of Q one.
But similarly x to the power it would be congruent to well, zero to the power which is zero.
And in March.
Q one.
So not very controversial to say in that case X to the power Eddie is congruent to x mod q10 is congruent
to zero we're saying there, but that is if xq1 divide x on the other hand, if Q one does not divide
x.
If Q one does not divide X, then we're going to use firm Arsenal theorem, Fermat's Little Theorem.
Okay, so one thing we're going to need first X to the power A and I'm interested in what that is equal
to.
And so X to the power.
A What is a what?
It's.
Q One minus one.
Multiply by Q two minus one.
So I'm going to put X to the power.
Q One minus one in a bracket, and then that's to the power.
Q Two minus one.
And that's because A is multiplying those two things together.
And in March.
Q One, I'm going to write on the far right hand side here.
Mar.
Q One just to remind us where we are in March.
Q One arithmetic.
We can use a thin central theorem here, so we've got an integer to the power prime minus one that becomes
a one in the bracket, and that is to the power.
Q Two minus one.
So that has changed into a one from Fair Master to seven.
And now we've got one to the power of something, which is one.
Okay.
So X and power A is congruent to one might.
Q one.
And now, since we know that e times D is equal to.
Okay.
A plus one.
In other words, e times d y where inverses of each other, which means we get this formula.
Then for some integer k we have.
Ex to the power, Eddie.
I wonder what's going to happen.
When it's congruent to x to the power k a plus one.
Yeah.
Which is congruent to.
If I break up that calculation, that would be X to the power A in a bracket to the power k.
And then multiply by X.
I say, Congressman, these are equal so far, all those are equal.
And then this is congruent to and this is where we can perform a substitution.
So again, in mod q one arithmetic, so I'm right in the right hand side, that bracket we can replace
with the previous line X to the power is congruent to one.
So that bracket is a one to the power K multiplied by x and that is congruent to one to the power case
one and multiply by x, so congruent to x.
And that is what I was trying to show.
Either way, we have this little congruence that I was trying to prove is true in Mod Q one and by the
completely, completely the same argument, it's going to be true in mod q to as well.
I don't actually have to say that argument again, because it's exactly the same.
It's just using one prime number instead of another.
So it's true in mod q one and it will be true in mod q two.
And since they are both prime, so since Q1 and Q2 of a prime, we're going to use our Chinese remainder
theorem, which means it's now true in mod m.
Which is equal to Q1 times Q2.
End of proof.
And.
Yes.
Okay.
I mean, you you'll need a moment to absorb this interview.
If you don't get it all straight away, I wouldn't expect you to.
But that should all be true.
If you take a moment to read back over it and absorb it in your own time.
That should all be true and working.
So we have a decryption method.
The decryption key is the multiplicative inverse of E and modulo a actually a decryption key.
In other words, if you want to find your decryption key, it is the coefficient of e in something like
s e plus t a equals one.
And how would you find this?
So we're looking for this s here.
The coefficient in front of E.
How would you find it?
You might just notice it if you are using small numbers.
If you notice, it's fine.
Great.
But otherwise you could use Euclid's algorithm.
Going back to the things we did in section one, the multiplicative ciphers.
You would use Euclid's algorithm so that you could write one as a combination of E and A, with that
coefficient being the value we are after for decryption.
So hopefully you can see that all that hard work we did in Section one was really laying the foundations
to set us up for this section.
Now here at the end.
So let's do an example of a decryption.
So let's have a equals four and E equals three as a bush.
So we're just using the example we had before when I encrypted a message with RSA and to remind you
A was for E equals three then.
Right, I need to write one as a combination of this you could use you create algorithm, although that
is those are small numbers.
So I think I could just notice that seven times three is 21 plus minus five times four is -20 is equal
to one.
So I might just notice that and go write this coefficient here in front of three is the decryption key
so we can use D equal seven.
I equal seven as our decryption key.
So we had the example before where I in cipher the message and the cipher turned out to be 107466.
And then you will hit that cipher with our decryption formula.
P is equal to C to the power d.
Okay, let's do that at seven.
So one to the power seven is one zero to the power seven is zero seven to the power seven.
Now it starts getting large.
And yeah, if you wanted to do this pen and paper by hand, you could break it up and find clever ways
of making parts of the calculation smaller or get a computer to do it.
And I am just going to laboriously write out what it is.
It's 823,543.
Now we'll go on to our next number four to the power seven.
Now, the big number, 16,384, six to the power seven.
Another big number, 279,000
279,936.
And we're going to get the same again here.
Right.
Modulo M and which is right back in the gap.
Modulo M.
So we're going to divide now by our modulus.
And in this small example, our modulus was ten.
Going back to our previous example.
So we divided by ten looking for the remainder, which is 103466.
Turn it back into letters.
You get the original message.
That egg that we had before and I say it will decrypt our message.
I will point something out here in the sentence underneath.
Notice I could have used a d equals three here as my decryption key.
And I could have I could have done this three times three is nine plus minus two times four is minus
eight, and that is equal to one.
So those are my values of eight and a three and four and the coefficient that is three in front of the
encryption key.
I just didn't want you to think that the encryption key and the decryption key D had to be the same
because in that small example there, the encryption and decryption key are both three.
That is not true in general.
That's why I kind of did it in a slightly different way here, just to make that point.
So there you have it and decryption keys.
And in practice, however, RSA is a relatively slow algorithm, so it is very used to encrypt plain
text messages directly.
So what I've shown you here is me and Cipher in a message using RSA, which is known as textbook RSA,
how, how you teach RSA, but you wouldn't actually use it in this way.
Instead, RSA is used to encrypt keys, so you can exchange keys with each other, and then you can
then have the key to use in whatever cipher you want to use the key in.
So you could use it in some sort of simpler cipher after that.
So in practice, I always say it's just another way of exchanging keys.
Right.
So that is encryption and decryption of RSA.
But we will be moving on next to breaking RSA.
Now, imagine you're the bad person here wanting to break one of these messages.
We're going to show you how hard it is to break RSA.