In this section, I would like to look at some of the methods you might use to break all this and what
we could do to prevent that from happening.
So if we look at our notes here, this is called Breaking RSA.
RSA encryption is incredibly strong provided we protect ourselves from some obvious attacks.
The first of which is frequency analysis.
If you remember the examples we were looking at before, I was actually encrypting a message letter
by letter, and as clever as RSA is, and that would still mean that we could break it by frequency
analysis the way I presented it at least.
So instead of encrypting one letter at a time, because that would still leave you vulnerable to simple
frequency attack, this problem is overcome by blocking or grouping the letters into blocks.
So let me show you an example of that.
So instead of just doing each letter or each number one at a time, we're going to sort of block them
together or group them together.
So that's E equal 47.
Okay.
This is a public key I'm giving you here equals 47 and M equals 150.
I like nice public information.
Numerically message bad egg if you remember that had these values 103466.
And yes, the way I did it before and you could see that there were some letters that were more common
than others.
But we could split this into three blocks of two letters, which would give us 1034 and 66.
And it's this these groups that are acted on by the cipher.
So what we would do is say ten to the power and then use our encryption key 47.
And you could calculate that however you want it to and the value you would get is 8034 to the power
47 and any Mod 115 would be 89 and 66 to the Power 47.
In Model 115 is 111.
So that would be the cipher text that I said.
It would be hiding the frequencies of the individual letters.
BLOCK Frequencies become more independent and more uniform as blocks get longer in ingress, blocks
of ten letters are proximately equally likely.
So if you can write your messages in blocks and then perform your calculations on those blocks instead.
That should prevent frequency analysis.
Let's have a look at this other attack here.
It's called chosen plaintext attack.
So this is very sneaky.
This is another way to break RSA is to encrypt likely plain text messages using the public key and then
seeing if they are equal to the ciphertext.
So you've stolen a ciphertext.
You think maybe it says, I don't know.
I think it says Attack London.
I can use the public key to see what attack London looks like in the cipher as a cipher.
And compare it with the ciphertext I stole.
So to prevent this, RSA typically embeds some form of structured randomized padding into the plaintext.
So when you're sending a message using RSA, you would stick in some fake symbols in there as well.
Yes.
Spread throughout the plaintext.
The padding ensures that the plaintext well encrypt to a large number of different possible ciphertext.
So you could have many different possible padding.
And then when you're encrypting these, you're going to get lots of different possibilities for your
ciphertext.
If we cannot distinguish between two ciphertext, even if they know or even if we know the original
plaintext, we say the cipher is semantically secure.
What I mean by that is imagine I gave you two cipher texts and I said, one of these says, Hello.
One of these says Goodbye.
Can you tell which one is which?
And you look at them and you see that they're the same length.
You don't notice any double letters or anything like that.
And you say, No, I can't tell which one is hello, which one is goodbye?
Then that is semantically secure.
In practice, this makes the cipher security equivalent to that of a one time pat cipher.
You're effectively saying these are equally likely to be hello or goodbye.
RSA with appropriate padding is semantically secure, which is a good thing.
I know that form of attack could be this cynical chosen ciphertext attack.
And I've got some gaps here, so let's take a look at this.
So let's say we are the spy trying to decrypt a cipher message.
I'm going to call it C one.
And we know that the cipher is RSA.
So it's a plain text message p to the power e.
In modern.
We could sneakily ask the holder of the private key to decrypt a different cipher.
I could say, Could you do me a favor?
Could you decrypt this cipher?
C two Now they would decrypt c two for you, but you've created this cipher and it is equal to or congruent
to C one.
Times x to the power e.
M mod m.
First some chosen integer x.
So I know E has public information.
I know m.
That's public information.
I've chosen a value for x, i whatever I want to choose.
I then take x to the power e I multiply by the cipher I've stolen.
Do that only mod and I've created a cipher a fake cipher could C2.
I then ask the private key holder to decrypt this for me please.
And if they do, the decryption will be p times x.
Modern.
So that's the result.
And they say, here you go, decrypted it.
It looks like this p x is what you're going to get.
And if because you know what X is, you can find the multiplicative inverse of x and you can cancel
that out and get P the original plain text message.
However, of course we can prevent that using padding schemes.
And here's an example something called okay, epi, optimal asymmetric encryption padding.
So it's just a method of including these fake symbols that prevent this kind of attack, this chosen
ciphertext attack.
And finally, here is another way you could break RSA Factorization.
This looks like an inherent flaw in RSA to me until you see what we're going to do.
Finally, RSA can be broken if we can find the original primes.
Q1 and Q2.
If you can work out the original primes, then if you've got them, then you can calculate a because
that's a simple thing is Q one minus one multiplied by Q2, minus one.
And if you can calculate A, you can use A and E, which is public information to find that multiplicative
decryption key D or multiplicative inverse of E, unfortunately, because M which is equal to Q one,
Q two, and that is public information.
We can find the original primes by factor ising.
And so now imagine the spy.
You take the public information, you've got an M as the modulus that tries it, you find the primes.
If you find the primes, you can find a and you can use A and E together to find the decryption key
and you've broken the code.
That does sound like an inherent flaw in the scheme because you do give away this modulus as free information.
And let's take a look at an example of you doing that.
So here's an example, kind of like one we saw before we had an encryption key which is equals 47 and
a modulus m equals 115.
And it's not that hard really to work out that 150 is equal to five times 23.
So I tried it and oh look, I've got two primes.
Once I've got the primes, I can now calculate a which is equal to five minus one is four multiplied
by 23 minus one is 22.
So A is equal to 88.
We can now use.
Well, whatever method you want.
I've used Euclid's algorithm here to calculate 15 times 47.
Plus.
Minus eight times 88.
Equals to one.
And that means the decryption key.
Is this bit here in front of the 47 D equals 15.
I've got the decryption key and now I can decrypt messages using that value.
Oh, dear.
However, this was possible because Q1 and Q2 the primes were quite small, relatively small.
And so that means that the end value, the modulus was quite quickly factionalised.
And the private key that was then found from the public key.
Private key.
It was found from the public key.
In reality, the primes used are much larger.
Right.
So this is something I wanted to show you as so.
And remember, this stuff is public information.
So if you go to something like Amazon or eBay or your online bank, you can go into the settings.
So you might go to your online bank's website.
And if you look at maybe the address bar, they often have a padlock symbol.
If you click on that, you will find something called the RSA key.
So it's there for you to find because it's public information, the public keys there, and you will
find those two numbers.
We've talked about the E value, the encryption value, and you find the modulus as well, the M value.
And that's what I did.
I went to my bank's website and I found those values.
The E value was something quite large, something like 65,000 and something bit the modulus values.
What I wanted to show you the modulus values.
Also, I know that large number and it's this number.
I've got it here.
So here it is.
This is the modulus used by my bank to send RSA keys.
And this is something that is something like 20,000 trillion.
Google.
Now, that is 100 digits there.
Google has another 100 digits there.
Google, another 100 digits.
Google.
There we go.
This huge number is actually 617 digits long.
Absolutely massive.
Right.
This is the value that my bank uses to send the RSA keys.
Absolutely.
Huge value.
And this modulus was made by multiplying two prime numbers together, but two very large prime numbers
together.
So to fracture ice, this becomes an incredibly hard problem.
Far too difficult to actually franchise this using a modern computer as so incredibly difficult problem
to work out.
And that's why they use these huge numbers.
And I'm talking like if you used a computer, it would take 30,000 years or something like that.
So this becomes a very difficult task.
And current RSA Keys, yes.
Would take modern computers thousands of years to factory.
So there you go.
That is the end of that section.
Finally, let's take a look at the next section, which is something called signatures.
How do we know if a message has actually come from the person we think it has?
Well, actually, there's a way to sign your message, and it uses the RSA method to prove who you say
you are.
Okay, I will see you in the next video.