It's time to take a look at the solutions for the RSA exercises.
And I start with a note saying that you are perfectly welcome to use a computer to work out these computations.
I recommend Wolfram Alpha dot com and that is exactly what I used when doing these calculations myself.
So there is no reason why you can't do that as well.
So we're going to encrypt the word lie in using RSA with modulus m equal 1241 and encryption key E equals
five and the result will be four numbers.
So let's take a look at that.
So Lyon is the word.
Going back to our animal names and we write that in numbers L becomes an 11, I becomes an eight oh,
becomes a 14 and becomes a 13.
And then what is the formula we're going to use when it's P to the power E and that is Mount M?
Like I said, I just use Wolfram Alpha for this.
And these were the values I got.
So 962 502.
471 and 234.
And that would be the ciphertext.
Let's take a look at question two.
We want to create an RSA scheme with two primes, Q1 and Q2, which are 23 and 179.
What is the modulus?
The modulus means multiplying those two primes together 23 times 179, and that is going to be 4117.
Using the scheme, calculate the value for a.
If you remember a is taking away one from each prime.
So we're looking at 23 minus one and multiplying that by 179 minus one.
And if we do that, that's 22 times 278 that that is equal to 3916.
And now using this scheme, what is the smallest possible choice of encryption key e.
So the important thing about the encryption key.
It must be prime to a.
That's right.
That in.
And what is a well, a is 3916, which if you break that down into its factors, it's two squared times
11 times 89.
So a good value for E would be equals three.
It is k prime and also it would be the smallest k prime value.
Perfect.
So this is using RSA and the smallest encryption key, encrypt the word forger.
So here we go.
Say the word is badger.
Be a d, g, e, r, which we are writing as numbers.
That is 136 417.
I know we're using our RSA formula, which is pizza power, a mod and.
And a lot of these are quite easy to work out because they're small numbers.
The E is three, so we're keeping these numbers to be one, a 0 to 27, a 216, we get a 64 and then
the only difficult one is the 17 cubed.
But I will tell you that the answer will be 796, and that's in mud and arithmetic.
So that is the final answer.
That will be your ciphertext.
Let's take a look at the next questions.
So question three.
Decrypt these numbers.
So we've got our ciphertext numbers using RSA with modulus m equals 187 and a decryption key D equals
three.
And then we should get letters of the alphabet.
We should get a message back.
So really this is the same procedure.
And if I write down the numbers first, it's the same procedure as before and we just using a decrypt
number now.
So we hit it with our formula is P to the power D in mod m and being 187.
And if we do that again, I just used Wolfram Alpha and we had 1914, 22, zero 13 and then that can
get turned into letters and it is t u c and it is two can.
Let's have a look at questions four and five.
We want to create an RSA scheme with two primes.
Q One is 60, 61 and.
Q two is 223.
What is the modulus?
The modulus is multiplying the primes together.
And we will get a modulus of 13,603 using this scheme.
Calculate the value of A to A equals.
61 minus one multiplied by 223 minus one.
So 60 times 222.
So that is going to be 13,320 if the encryption key is quite big.
Number 1903, what is the decryption key?
So to do this, we need to know a formula.
We need to work out an expression of this.
Form one equals three times E plus t, a, and then B here the coefficient of E will be the decryption
key.
And that can be done with Euclid's algorithm.
There it is again.
So let's have a go at that.
So using Euclid's algorithm, first of all, we're going to put our values for a on the left hand side
is Y 13,320, and that is going to be equal to make something.
Times 1903 plus something and that sort of thing here turns out to be a sexist coefficient and a remainder
of 1902.
And now if you shift things across 1903 is equal to you can be one lot of 1902 plus one.
Not actually ends Euclid's algorithm already.
That's nice.
And now we reversed that so that we can write one is equal to 1903 -1902.
And we'll just replace.
1902.
With the previous line which was replaced 1902.
Replace it with 13,320 minus six.
Lots of 1903.
And we clean this up so we'll have a plus six, lots of 1903 plus the one we had at the beginning.
So that is a plus seven lots.
Of 1903 minus the 13,320.
And is this coefficient in front of the 1903, which was the encryption key?
So a d is equal to seven.
I gave you a relatively small number to work with that.
So we're going to use that decryption key now to decrypt our final, final ciphertext, which is here.
So let's do that.
So it's these numbers.
12,521.
12,397.
10,139 and 99.
And we're going to use our decryption key.
So each of our data is now seven in model.
And we worked out in part A and if we do that again, I just used a computer to do it.
It was 15, 14, 13 and 24.
And that will be give us a P, o and Y.
I've given you a pony.
How nice.
And finally, question five.
Same idea, really?
Just with hard numbers.
So question five.
We want to create an RSA scheme with these primes.
So slightly bigger primes now.
Hundred 13 257.
The modulus is multiplying those together.
Which if we do multiply those together, it's 29,041 a.
Means subtracting one from each prime and multiplying that together.
Which if we do, that will give us a value.
28,672.
And now we've got an encryption key, which is this 18,847.
What is the decryption key?
Same method as before.
Just larger numbers.
And it can be done with Euclid's algorithm.
So we're going to use Euclid's algorithm exactly the same way as before to calculate this.
The answer actually has one, two, three, four, five, six steps in it, and then you reverse those.
I'm not going to write them out just for brevity, but the complete solution is in the resources with
this video.
So I will just skip to the end and tell you that after reversing Euclid's algorithm, you get one equals
607 multiplied by the 18,847
-399, multiplied by the value for a which is the 28,000.
672.
And it's the coefficient here in front of E which is 607, so D equals 607.
That is your decrypt key.
And then I do ask you to decrypt a message.
Using that decryption key.
And if we do that, well, there's no surprises here.
So these are our numbers.
And we are going to use the computer to help us out.
And there is a zero there.
So that should be a correlate.
And if I just write in these numbers.
Yes.
Our formula is just as before because the decryption key is 607 and we get 15 four zero 13.
20 and 19.
What do we get?
We get p e a.
And you two.
Yeah, we got peanut.
How nice.
Okay, so that is our essay.
And next, we'll be looking at breaking RSA.