Now it's time to take a look at the solutions for the TV helmet exercises.
So I've asked that you try and calculate these consequences without a calculator.
So do hope you did try that.
Question one says Calculate the lowest positive value of three to power for mod 80.
So if I write three to the power for that is equal to or counting to 81 which is congruent to one mod
eight six fairly simple to start with be use your answer to the above to show that three to the power
316 is coming to one mod 80.
So we can break down three to the power 360.
It's three to the power, four to the power 79.
And that is congruent to now we replace the three to the power four with one and that is to the power
79, and that is congruent to at one mod 80.
There you go.
That is the end of the proof question to show that forward to the power five and plus one is to zero
mod 1024 for all integers.
N.
So let's try that.
Well, we start by observing that 4 to 2 power five is 1024, which is congruent to zero mod 1 to 4.
So if we're interested in four to the power five and plus one, we can break that down and we can write
as four to the power, five to the power n multiplied by four.
And that is congruent to well the bracket gets replaced with a zero to the power end times four and
that is coming to zero times four.
That is zero in mod 1 to 4 and that's always true for any integer n.
Question three Calculate 11 to the power and Model 101 for these values of DN two, three, four, five
and ten.
So let's do that.
Let's start with 11 squared.
So 11 squared is equal to 121.
Nice.
Congruent to 20.
In mod 101.
Now we look at the next power it having cubed.
Well we can use the answer we've had before so we can look at 11 squared and then multiply that by 11,
replacing the 11 squared with 20 and then multiply that by 11 we get 220 and that is congruent to 18
MOD 101.
If we go to the next power and even to the power four, you could break that up in many different ways.
I'm going to have a look at 11 squared.
Squared.
So if that is congruent to replace the bracket with 20 and then we'll square that, that will give us
400.
And in this, we'll get 97 MOD 101.
And if we look at 11 to the power five, again, you can break this up in many different ways.
I'm going to look at 11 squared times.
11 cubed.
11 squared can be replaced with 2011 cubed can be replaced with 18.
So we get 360.
And that is congruent to 57.
Mod 101.
And finally, we're looking at 11 to the power ten.
Again, you can break that up in many ways.
What I've done is Dr. 11 to the powerful square that to get 11 to the power eight and then multiply
by 11 squared and that is congruent to what 11 to power for it was 97.
But I'm going to actually write that as minus four, because that's going to make my life easier.
And that becomes squared.
And then multiply that by 11 squared, which becomes 20.
So we're going to get 16 times 20.
16 times 20, which is 320, and then that is congruent to 17 MOD 101.
So it is a little bit of a scale, but you can actually do these calculations by hand.
Now let's take a look at question four.
So here is question four.
And we're going to use Steffi Howe in key exchange to create a shared key.
We've got a generator X equal to 11 and a modulus Q equal to 101.
So first of all, we're going to create Alice's shared key.
So if Alice's secret integer is a equals 13, calculate X to the power aid mode.
Q So we're looking at 11 to the power.
A So that is to the power 13 in Mod 101 so we can use the answers we've already worked out to help us
out here.
So that's could be written as 11 to the power, ten times 11 cubed or any other way that you want to
do it.
But 11 to the power, ten is 17.
11, Kate becomes 18.
And then you can calculate that it's 306.
Which is congruent to three mod one I want.
Now we look at Bob's part of this.
Bob's secret integer is Big 20, and we can perform the same sort of calculation 11 to the power 20.
So how could we break that down?
We could look at 11 to the power of ten and then square that 11 to the power ten where 1717 squared
is 289.
And then that will become 87 MOD 101.
Finally we are going to calculate the shared secret X to the power A Times B and that is in mod Q.
Now you could do this by looking at Alices part of the secret first and then using Bob's secret number.
Or you could do that the other way round.
I am going to start with Alice's secret.
Seems easier, so Alice's part of the secret was three.
And then we will base that to Bob secret number, which was 23 to the power 20.
Now, I didn't really find an easy way of doing this calculation, but I did it this way.
We could break that up as three to the power four to the power five, which could be written as 81 to
the Power five, which in this modulus, which is 101, I'm going to write that as -20 to the power
five.
Then that can be calculated fairly easy because it's a nice round number.
It's -3 million, 200,000.
So that is a big number.
But the modulus is very easy.
So with a bit of work you can actually show that that is congruent to 84 and mod one I want.
And.
Why can't we use the generator x equals ten and thus because it will not generate all possible values
in modulo 101.
Just to show that we can look at ten squared.
And that is going to be 100.
In mod one I want.
Ten.
Cute.
It's going to be 91.
In Mod 101.
Ten to the power for.
It's going to be one.
Marge 101 and ten to the power five.
And it turns out to be ten in my 101.
And from there, the pattern will repeat.
So we're not generating all the possible values.
Another way to see that is to notice that ten squared, which is 100, is congruent to minus one in
mod 101.
So tend to the power for it's going to be coming to minus one squared, which is one in mod 101 and
therefore a ten to the power for pn where any some integer that is going to be common to one mod 101
no matter what the integer is.
So again, you're not generating all the possible values there.
Okay.
Next, we're going to be looking at all a.