Let me go back to this idea of a locked box one more time.
So this time imagine I want to give everyone a box for free.
Everyone can have a box and everyone can have a padlock.
I'm giving away padlocks.
Everyone can have one.
And if you want to send me a secret message, put it in the box, lock it with the padlock and send
it to me.
So that means if it's stolen, it is locked with a padlock.
But if someone wants to steal a key, they can't.
Because I didn't give anyone a key.
Only I have a key, a secret private key that I can use to unlock the padlock.
So this is the idea of RSA, but let's take a look at how that might look mathematically.
So we'll go to our notes for this.
So what I'm going to do is give you the procedure for RSA for this read this sentence to start off with.
If it is practically impossible to deduce the decryption key from the encryption key, then the system
is called asymmetric.
This allows you to freely publish the encryption key known as the public key while keeping the decryption
key secret known as the private key.
RSA is an example of an asymmetric system.
So essentially this is like having a padlock.
So there's one method for locking and then there is another key for unlocking which and it's very difficult
to work out the decryption key for the encryption key.
So let's describe the general routine using the smallest possible number.
So I'm just going to describe how this procedure works.
So RSA set up.
So we need two prime numbers and I'm going to call these prime numbers.
Q one.
And Q2 is our prime members and we're going to set em to equal Q1 times.
Q2, we're going to set something called A to equal Q1.
Minus one in a bracket multiplied by Q two minus one in a bracket like that.
And we're going to choose a number E.
Which is less than encode prime to a.
All right.
That is the setup.
So we have two prime numbers and then all these things are deduced from those two prime numbers.
And so the encryption key can be any number, but it has to be less than and k prime to eight now to
encrypt.
So if we want to encrypt a plaintext letter P as a ciphertext, that's a C, we use this formula c.
It's congruent to p to the power e at mod m.
Sir.
E is your encryption key, and in many ways you can think of that formula as being very similar to the
additive encryption formula, the multiplicative encryption formula that we saw way back in Section
one.
But this time we're not adding, we're not multiplying, we're taking the plaintext value and raising
to a power.
So the numbers E and M.
Published and former public key to insight for the message.
Everyone's allowed to know it.
So when you create this cipher, you can just give away the value E and M so that other people can send
you secret messages.
Example.
So let.
Q one equal to.
That's a prime number and.
Q to.
Equals five.
That's another prime number.
Then what is our setup?
We have M, which is our modulus.
M is equal to two times five.
You multiply the primes and you get ten, obviously.
And A and a is equal to.
Well, we subtract one from each of the primes and then multiply.
So it's one times four, which is equal to four.
And now we're going to choose an exponent or an encryption key e equals.
Now it has to be less than and k prime to a.
In this small example, we don't really have many choices.
So equals three.
We would have choices when by using larger numbers, but the numbers that we are going to work with
do have to be less than the value of and the modulus.
So I'm going to send you a message, but I'm restricted here because I've only got a small example,
so I'm going to use letters less than ten.
So here's the message.
Bad egg.
Okay, so unfortunately, I had a bad breakfast.
I'm sending the message bad egg.
And in numerical values, then bees are one, a 0 to 3 and so on.
And now I'm going to hit that with a formula.
The formula is cipher is congruent to.
AP could power e in March or an ease before I'm actually breaking up the mojo steps, I'm going to e
Peter Power E first and so E is three.
So I'm keeping the numbers.
Okay, so one cubed is 102203 cubed is 27 three times three times three four cubed four times four times
four is 64 and six cubed.
I will tell you is 216 and 216 again.
So that's P to the power E and now we're going to do the modulo step and that is my ten.
Oh, well, that's easy.
My ten because it's the remainder of the division by ten.
It's just the last digit.
So that's going to be a one as 07a for a six and a six.
And that would be the cipher you sent.
So you send that as your message.
And so that's the procedure.
It's really not that difficult.
It's no more difficult than the multiplicative, not really, or the additive ciphers that were raised
to an exponent here.
But we're going to look at how you decrypt this message next.
Now, this is where we're going to do quite a lot of work.
So there is quite a lot of work involved in decrypting these messages.
In fact, let's just take a look at what we need to decrypt a message.
So moving on to our next section RSA decryption, we're going to have to find a decryption key.
I call it D for decryption such that this is what we want.
The plaintext is congruent to C to the power.
D So it's the same procedure mod m but it's just reversing what we did before.
So if I hit it on the cipher, I get the original plaintext letter back.
So in other words, we need to find this number d such that.
So I want the plaintext to be congruent to C to the power D And what is c0c is plaintext to the power
e in brackets and in that is to the power of D, but that is congruent to or equal to p to the power
e times D because that's how exponents work, that's how powers work.
And this will be in mod m arithmetic.
So that's what we're looking for.
We're looking for some value where that is true, the next three results will show that D exists and
how to find it.
But I think we'll take a pause here and I'll put the results in the next video.
We're going to have some actual proper mathematical results which have proper mathematical names.
The code firm has a little theorem and the Chinese remainder theorem.